Good morning, everybody. My name is Michael Noragard. I'm from Denmark, currently living in Madison, Wisconsin. And I'll be talking to you today in a little tale about the return of the wolf into the Danish wildlife. The title of the presentation is the Danish word. It's pronounced Ulvetider.
It means really wolf times and the other meaning of that word is that it's hard times for the population. When the Danish population is going through wolf times, it means that it's tough times for the population. Some of the words you will see on the charts here are really Danish words and Danish letters and I'll just write to you so you can see some of the letters so you don't get confused.
There's a Danish letter called Æ which is really a mix of an A and an E in English. You will also see a Danish letter called Æ and that letter is really an O and an E put together. And the final Danish letter that you may see in some of the slides is Danish Æ.
very difficult to pronounce for a non-Danish person. Again, it's an U and that is really a combination of two A's together. And some of these characters could show up in the slides you will see in a second. So let me get started by just showing you on this chart here, the first chart. Where is Denmark? Denmark is a little country and the northern part of Europe shown on red on this first chart.
It is having a border to the southern side, which is with Germany. And to the right east part of Denmark on this chart, you see Sweden, which is a whole country stretching to the north. And even further north of Denmark and across the sea, you'll find Norway. The Danish population is around 5 million. Compared to Sweden, which is a neighboring country, you have around 8.5 million.
so relatively densely populated country. Let me start the tale about the return of the wolf to Denmark to when it all started around 15,000 years ago. 15,000 years ago Northern Europe was seeing the ice from the Ice Age retracting and what you have here
What is now Denmark and northern part of Germany was at that point I covered by the tundra and Along with the tundra and the ice retracting you saw the reindeer's moving in and with the reindeer's The wolves came along so the wolves have been existing in northern Europe since the retraction of the ice approximately 10 15,000 years ago and as
Just as a lot of other animals in northern Europe, wolves have been extinct in Denmark for many, many years now. The history of the wolves in Denmark really started, as I mentioned, immigrated with the reindeer in early age. It was quite commonly spread across the Danish countryside until late 17th century.
But it was very widely hunted throughout the 18th century, and finally it was extinct in 1813, where the last wolf was killed through hunting in Denmark. So it has really been absent from the Danish nature for more than or up to 200 years.
Tell from the headline of this presentation, the wolf made a re-entry and re-immigrated into Denmark in 2012. The first picture of the wolf being spotted in Denmark was taken in November of 2012 in a natural habitat in Denmark, in the northern part of Jotland. This animal, this wolf here, was later found dead
And there was a DNA test conducted on the wolf which showed that this particular wolf had actually wandered all the way to northern part of Jotland from eastern part of Germany. And I'll just show you on this chart here where it's been walking all the way from eastern part of Germany through
across the borderline to Denmark and up to the northern part of Denmark. So it's a pretty significant achievement, but not unusual for a wolf or wolf family to wander long distances. The kind of wolf that lives in northern Europe is a European wolf. It's called a gray wolf. There are other wolf species in northern America, which vary slightly in size and
And not least in the appearance, the colors are typically darker. You can find a black wolf in North America. As mentioned, a lot of hype initially when the first wolf was spotted in Denmark. This picture is the second picture taken by a wolf spotted in a typical Danish farm country area. It's a good illustration, not only of the wolf, but also of what a Danish countryside looks like.
Not very isolated, you have the windmills which are quite common in Denmark. In the background here and in the front of the picture you have a typical Danish agricultural landscape. So this wolf here is really wandering, walking across the farm country. One of the other early observations that cost a lot of attention in Denmark and the media was this
these bones found from a red deer that was eaten by a wolf. And what happened was that this red deer, there was a DNA sample taken from the bone shield that actually proved that it had been eaten by a wolf in the Danish wildlife and that it's this wolf that had eaten this
Red deer originated from the eastern part of Germany called Saxon that I mentioned to you before and showed on the map here. So this animal, this wolf that killed this particular deer was one of the same family or maybe it was the one that you saw in the picture that I showed previously. This is probably the photo that caused the most attention in Denmark when it was popularized. This is taken from
So-called photo trap in Denmark, which works as if there's an animal approaching the trap that a picture is taking of the animal. And where this wolf has been spotted is very close to an area where
feeding station for red deers and other deers in the Danish wildlife. So you can say this wolf was probably attracted to the smell of these and the appearance of the red deers at this particular place. And as you can see on this picture, this wolf is actually shredding the most of its fur. It's changing from the winter fur to the summer fur.
Looking at the Danish map, this is where you have had the initial observations of wolf in 2012 and 2013. The blue spots indicate where the wolf has with certainty been proved as present, whereas the red ones have not scientifically been proved, but they have been observed by human beings.
It is supposed to be scientifically proven. Either there's been a photo taken of the particular wolf or there's been a DNA sample. One can't be very surprised in reality. Even though it has caused a lot of attention, we shouldn't be that surprised that the wolf has made its arrival back in Denmark. If you look at this map here of Germany and Poland, Germany to
which is Germany and to the right east part of this map you have Poland. You will see that there are quite a number of wolf families that have been observed. The family is where you have the thick green lines and with the thinner green lines is where you have individual wolves living in Germany and Poland. A typical habitat for the wolf in Denmark would look
have to look like this. It's not very common in Denmark, but there are a number of areas which I'll show on one of the following charts where this kind of conditions exist. The typical Danish countryside looks more like this, which is farmland in the winter time.
And this is not a typical area where the wolf would like to live on a permanent basis. But of course it can use these farmlands to cross from one habitat to the other. And it can easily walk long distances across these farm farmlands in order to get to the areas that they prefer. As mentioned previously, one of the reasons why this tale is interesting is that the
Return of the Wolf to Denmark did get a lot of attention and it is actually still getting a lot of attention in the Danish media. There have been newspaper articles, there have been news reportings in the main Danish TV channels and this article shown here is actually from one of the biggest TV channels in Denmark. It's from late 2012 showing one of the pictures, early pictures of photos of
a wolf in Denmark. So why is it causing such a lot of attention? I think it has to do with wolves causing people to be scared. Maybe not only for themselves but also because of animals that they have on farms or dogs and cats that there may be potential prey of the wolves.
As said, I think a lot of the concern has to do with, within a lot of people, at least in Denmark, there's a little nervousness about the wolves. And it may come from our childhoods, where we were often told the stories about the little red, red, red riding hood who went to the grandma's house to only find that the wolf was in her bed and had eaten her grandmother.
And I think a lot of Danish people had actually either read or been told this story when they were little. And I think deep inside in you, when you're an adult, you still remember these stories. There are others, there's Peter and the wolf and the English term don't cry wolf. I mean, it's just kind of the same logic behind it. You have to be afraid of the wolf and it is a dangerous animal.
How much do the wolves eat? Typically, one wolf eat around 412 pounds of meat, which if there were 70 wolves a year, sorry, in Denmark, if there were 70 wolves in Denmark, that would correspond to around 100 to 250,000 pounds of meat annually. And that number should be seen in comparison with the annual hunting in Denmark, which is around 5 million pounds of meat.
So it's around one twentieth of that. Not only is the concern about potential reappearance of the wolf and the Danish nature coming from individuals that are concerned about their childs or their children or their own life so to speak, but more often some of the concerns come from the farmers. Cows are quite common in Denmark and
Generally speaking, the cows are really not much at risk, as you'll see from some statistics on a chart following the next one. What is more at risk is the sheep. Often the sheep are living in more rural areas and more isolated, not with a lot of human interaction, where they feed in the summertime. And I mean, they would be more vulnerable and more obvious targets for the wolves.
And that is really also confirmed by the Swedish observations. And you will see through the first right on this chart, the average number of animals that were attacked and killed by wolves. 19 dogs were attacked and killed by wolves in Sweden on average the last 10 years. 180 close to 200 sheep killed annually.
and cattle, not very many, only around four and a half on average over the last 10 years. So it's really confirming what I talked about before that. The main target of the wolf in the farm country is really the sheep. The simple rule in Denmark is that it is prohibited actually to do any sort of hunting of wolves. It is totally protected and all kind of hunting of wolves is illegal.
If a person violates the legislation, the person could go to jail for two years and of course lose any sort of hunting privileges or permissions which you need in Denmark in order to go hunting. And of course also a confiscation of weapons. So again, it's not allowed to do any sort of hunting. And I think more relevant,
The discussion is if there's any sort of compensation made for farmers or people that see their livestock attacked by wolves. And I believe that there's legislation in place now which will give people opportunity to get some sort of compensation by the government on the authorities if attacks happen on sheeps or cattle or any other
farm animal, whereby wolves. So this is really the end of the tale around the return of the wolf into Denmark. It is still causing a lot of attention and media coverage. The population is really split between the wildlife lovers that would like to see the wolf appear more widely in Denmark.
in the Danish nature and farmers and other concern or some concern individuals that feel threatened by the wolves and see and are just really expecting or waiting for the first killing of a human being by a wolf in Denmark. With that I'm going to stop the recording and wish you all a nice day.